{"tossups": [{"question": "This ruler gained control of Burgundy in the Treaty of Madrid shortly after defeating his rival at Pavia. He won the Battle of Muhlberg against the Schmalkaldic League while attempting to halt the Reformation in Germany, but eventually allowed for some religious autonomy in the Peace of Augsburg. This ruler summoned Martin Luther to the Diet of Worms. For ten points, name this 16th century monarch who served as both King of Spain and Holy Roman Emperor.", "answer": "<b> Charles V</b>, Holy Roman Emperor (accept<b> Carlos I</b> of Spain or<b> Charles I of Spain</b>, but don\u2019t prompt on Charles I alone; prompt on Charles or Carlos)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "An aristocrat boards a train bound for this region to follow the woman he loves, a prostitute who was tricked into giving a womanizing merchant a lethal dose of arsenic. This region is the setting of the later parts of the novel<em> Resurrection</em>. Sonya Marmeladova travels to this region near the end of<em> Crime and</em> <em>Punishment</em>. For ten points, name this region to which Raskolnikov is exiled to complete a sentence of eight years of hard labor.", "answer": "<b> Siberia</b> (prompt on (Eastern) Russia)", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Long Fiction"}, {}, {"question": "A thunderbird replaced a yellow version of this symbol on a red diamond as the insignia of the 45th Infantry Division, which consisted of National Guardsmen from the American southwest. This symbol, whose name derives from Sanskrit for \u201causpicious,\u201d was used by the Thule Society, which supported the DAP, or German Worker\u2019s Party. For ten points, name this four-armed symbol, common in numerous religious traditions, that was adopted by the Nazi Party.", "answer": "<b> swastika</b> (accept<b> tetraskelion</b>; accept<b> hakenkreuz</b> or<b> hooked cross</b>; accept<b> fylfot</b>; accept tetra<b>gammadion</b>; do not accept or prompt on cross alone)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "For ten points, name this first major rebellion in colonial Virginia.", "answer": "<b> Bacon</b>\u2019s Rebellion Page 1", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "People who were not in one of these organizations revolted in Florence during the Ciompi [chomp-ee] Revolt. An alliance of these organizations formed a trading league in the Baltic Sea called the Hanseatic League. Some members of these organizations progressed from apprentices to journeymen to master craftsmen. For ten points, name these town-based medieval associations of merchants and skilled laborers.", "answer": "<b> guild</b>s", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "A leader of this religion named James Strang established a controversial \u201ckingdom\u201d on Beaver Island in Lake Michigan in the mid 19th Century. A leader of this religion founded the territorial capital of Fillmore after his plans to found the state of Deseret fell through. Members of this religion were led to Nauvoo, Illinois by Joseph Smith and then to Salt Lake City by Brigham Young. For ten points, name this religion whose members founded the Utah Territory.", "answer": "<b> Mormon</b>ism (accept word forms; accept the Church (of Jesus Christ) of<b> Latter Day Saints</b>; accept<b> LDS</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "An 1889 attempt to build a railway along this location ended when Frank Brown drowned exploring it. John Powell named this location after leading the first American expedition to its ground floor. The glass-bottomed \u201cSkywalk\u201d is maintained by the Hualapai tribe in this location, which was regarded as sacred by the ancestral Pueblo that first inhabited it. The Colorado River formed, for ten points, what 277-mile long canyon in Arizona?", "answer": "<b> Grand Canyon</b> Page 2", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "This man rented the Kennedy Farm in Maryland under the alias of Isaac Smith. Forces under this man defeated a contingent under Henry Pate in the Battle of Black Jack and killed several members of the Doyle family in the Pottawatomie Massacre. This man cut off telegraph cables and railroad lines as part of his raid on a Virginia arsenal. For ten points, name this abolitionist who was executed in 1859 for leading a raid on Harpers Ferry.", "answer": "John<b> Brown</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "For ten points, name this Roman goddess of beauty and counterpart to Aphrodite.", "answer": "<b> Venus</b> (accept<b> Venus</b> of Willendorf; accept Rokeby<b> Venus</b>; accept<b> Venus</b> de Milo; accept <b>Aphrodite</b>, alone or with the other additional information here, until \u201cRoman\u201d is read)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "This man sought and received aid from Haitian president Alexandre P\u00b4etion in exchange for adopting an emancipation policy. This leader\u2019s Organic Decree cemented his status as president-liberator of one polity. This politician wrote the Cartagena Manifesto shortly before leading the Admirable Campaign. After liberating his homeland at the Battle of Carabobo, this man met at Guayaquil with Jos\u00b4e de San Mart\u00b4\u0131n. For ten points, name this Venezuelan liberator of many South American countries.", "answer": "Sim\u00b4on (Jos\u00b4e Antonio de la Sant\u00b4\u0131sima Trinidad de)<b> Bol\u00b4\u0131var</b> (y Palacios)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "An 1864 raid on this city failed to relieve prisoners at Irving Block Prison. One of this city\u2019s parks was hastily renamed Health Sciences Park in 2013; that park was the site of a Charles Niehaus equestrian statue overlooking a pair of graves. In December 2017, to avoid a state law banning war memorial changes on public property, this city sold two of its parks to a non-profit that then took down the aforementioned Confederate memorial and a statue of Jefferson Davis. Jim Strickland is the mayor of, for ten points, what Tennessee city on the Mississippi River?", "answer": "<b> Memphis</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This woman\u2019s note in<em> The Times</em> convinced Isambard Kingdom Brunel to build the Renkioi facility shortly after this figure arrived at the Selimiye Barracks. While working at Scutari, this woman cut the death rate in half after implementing techniques like hand-washing. This woman\u2019s service in the Crimean War granted her the nickname \u201cLady with the Lamp.\u201d For ten points, name this British woman, often considered the founder of modern nursing.", "answer": "Florence<b> Nightingale</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "In this state, over 150 Wintu natives were killed during the Bridge Gulch Massacre. Lawrence Graham led an expedition into what is now this state following the Southern Emigrant Trail. Samuel Brannan amassed a fortune operating stores in this state, where Levi Strauss got his start selling dry goods. A discovery made at Sutter\u2019s Mill triggered the migration of the \u201cForty-Niners\u201d to, for ten points, what West Coast state, where population booms hit cities like Sacramento?", "answer": "<b> California</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This country\u2019s Keroman peninsula is the site of three submarine pens, two of which required subs to be taken out of the water completely. The success of Operation Cobra in this country led to the creation of the Falaise Pocket. Canadian soldiers launched the failed Dieppe Raid into this country, where hedgerows later hindered tanks during attempts to take Caen. For ten points, name this country, the site of the Normandy landings during World War II.", "answer": "<b> France</b> (accept Vichy<b> France</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>This military force was sponsored by Pope Sixtus V, who treated it as a crusade and gave its sponsors a subsidy. Prior to this force\u2019s expected deployment of the Army of Flanders, its opponents were (+) rallied by the Tilbury Speech. The Duke of Medina Sidonia commanded this force, which was designed to prevent interference in the (*)</b> Netherlands but was devastated at the Battle of Gravelines. Elizabethan England was targeted by, for ten points, what fleet launched in 1588 by Philip II of Spain?", "answer": "the Spanish<b> Armada</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This scientist built on the work of Edward (*) </b> Jenner to develop vaccines against anthrax and rabies. For ten points, name this French scientist whose namesake process heats food to kill harmful microorganisms in foods like milk.", "answer": "Louis<b> Pasteur</b>", "metadata": "Science - Biology"}, {"question": "<b>A member of this family replaced William Belknap as Secretary of War under Ulysses Grant. John F. Kennedy\u2019s</b><em><b> Profiles in Courage</b></em><b> commended a senator from this family for</b> <b>criticizing the (+)</b> <b>Nuremberg Trials; that senator from this family co-sponsored a 1947</b> <b>labor relations act with Fred (*)</b> Hartley. The Chief Justice of the Supreme Court for almost all of the 1920s was from this family. For ten points, name this Ohio family of Alphonso and Robert, as well as William Howard, who succeeded Theodore Roosevelt as president.", "answer": "<b> Taft</b> family (accept Alphonso<b> Taft</b>; accept William Howard<b> Taft</b>; accept Robert<b> Taft</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "An earlier sack of this city was carried out by (*)</b> Tamerlane in 1398. For ten points, name this seat of the Mughal Empire, a city whose \u201cNew\u201d district now hosts the government of Narendra Modi as the capital city of India.", "answer": "<b> Delhi</b> (accept<b> New Delhi</b><em> after</em> \u201c\u2019New\u2019 district\u201d is read)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This artist sang \u201cIt don\u2019t take too much high IQ\u2019s to see what you\u2019re doing to me\u201d in her appearance in the original</b><em><b> Blues Brothers</b></em><b> film. This singer, who performed \u201cMy Country,</b> <b>\u2018Tis of Thee\u201d at the (+)</b> <b>2009 inauguration of President Obama, received the Presidential</b> <b>Medal of Freedom in 2005 for a career that included 11 Grammys for Best Female (*)</b> R&B Vocal Performance. For ten points, name this \u201cQueen of Soul\u201d whose hits include \u201cThink,\u201d \u201cChain of Fools,\u201d and \u201cRespect.\u201d", "answer": "Aretha<b> Franklin</b> (prompt on Aretha)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "<b>Josef Terboven helped run this country during its Nazi occupation. The Nazi invasion of this country was discovered after the sinking of the</b><em><b> Rio de Janeiro</b></em><b> off the coast of (+) Lillesund; during that invasion, a failed coup in this country was announced over the radio, the first such event in history. The Nazi invasion of (*) </b> Denmark was simultaneous with the invasion of, for ten points, what Scandinavian country where a pro-Nazi puppet government was led by Vidkun Quisling west of Sweden?", "answer": "<b> Norway</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>This man\u2019s death was indirectly caused by the publishing of Charles D. Cooper\u2019s letters.</b> <b>James Callender wrote about this man\u2019s affair with Maria [mah-RYE-uh] (+)</b> <b>Reynolds.</b> <b>This man, who urged consolidation of state and federal debt in his \u201cFirst Report on Public Credit,\u201d joined George (*)</b> Washington to put down a rebellion in Pennsylvania over a whiskey tax that this man implemented. The First Bank of the United States was founded by, for ten points, what first Secretary of the Treasury who was killed in a duel with Aaron Burr?", "answer": "Alexander<b> Hamilton</b> ", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>In a case involving Santa Clara County and one of these entities, John Marshall</b> <b>Harlan concluded fences could not be included in taxes on these entities. Theodore</b> <b>Judah was a member of the \u201cBig (+)</b> <b>Four\u201d who built one of these projects. The</b> <b>Gadsden Purchase was initially acquired to build a southern one of these structures.</b> <b>During President (*) </b> Grant\u2019s administration, the Credit Mobilier scandal concerned, for ten points, what type of project built by the Union Pacific company?", "answer": "<b> rail</b>roads (accept additional information relating to a transcontinental<b> rail</b>road only after \u201cTheodore\u201d is read)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}